hello welcome to the B&B connection uh
this is episode four right Brad number
four yeah is this number four so we
actually recorded uh this
episode last uh Wednesday no last Friday
but uh the audio didn't work for some
reason I just got a Mac computer and I
don't know what happened but we just did
a test and the audio was working working
so hopefully we have to recreate that
magic now yeah so but it was a great
episode so we hope that uh it's still
just as good so um all right I got to
keep track of time so it's
4:45 Brad we have till 5:15 then we got
to stop okay so today's to uh today's U
podcast is going to be on variety and
training um we had an email from
somebody who asked us to do a a podcast
on like functional subdivisions in
muscles and how you know different parts
of muscles work uniquely and so you
should train them uh
uniquely and we didn't feel like that
would make a Whole 30 Minute Podcast so
we just were going to talk about Variety
in general so first up we're going to
talk about kind of what what functional
differentiation is or what um what did
you call it Brad compartment
compartments or
compartmentalization segmentation yeah
it says different names in the
literature but basically what it means
is different parts of muscles work
differently depending on the movement so
you can have one movement stress one
part of a muscle and another movement
that works the same muscle group stress
another part so I guess
uh we've kind of always assumed this in
bodybuilding bodybuilders have always
done things to stress certain
areas and then for some reason kind of
like a decade ago we saw a backlash
against this and you saw all these
people say it doesn't matter if you just
work a muscle pick any exercise you're
going to work all the you know the whole
muscle and muscles run the length of the
whole like the muscular tendon tendonous
unit goes from one end to the other so
you're going to activate all the fibers
in it and that's just wrong
I will say uh Jose Antonio wrote an
awesome paper on this in what was it
2000 Brad yeah so that was 12 years ago
he wrote an awesome paper 13 Miss C 13
oh yeah it's 2013 I do that all the time
sometimes I forget how old I am um Brad
do you remember the name of that
paper oh I don't
Regional but it was a classic Regional
hypertrophy
something like that and and he went into
it wasn't just about the uh functional
differentiation um which certainly is a
big part of it but uh he talked about
all the different aspects one one of my
favorite articles jscr was a review
article my second favorite article on
hypertrophy next to
yours but really the two of them do a
pretty darn good job of summarizing
about now here's what's crazy is he
wrote that 13 years ago but now there's
so much more evidence in the last in the
last two years
Alone um as most people know I have a
research review service I can't tell you
how many articles I've come across we've
reviewed a lot of them on the site
probably
like uh 10 of them at least in the last
two years uh talking about this concept
now so here's what's it's it dep you
know like it's common sense with some
muscles but not with others so like
anyone knows that if you're going to
work the deltoids you would need to do
like one exercise like say front raises
Mike work work the front delts more and
if you wanted to work the side delts
you'd want to do like lateral raises
maybe hold on though BR you you're kind
of J because that's a different animal
that's not about the functional
differentiation you're talking about the
whole muscle here I think what you're
referring to in the other context is the
segmentation of a given muscle so really
that's that's kind of apples and oranges
that we can get into as a ECT of variety
and certainly that's an important reason
why you should not just do one movement
for each uh area as some people think
but the issue that you're talking about
if you want to just go a little further
with that is the fact that muscles don't
span what contrary to popular belief
they don't necessarily just span from
origin to insertion and they're often
subdivided by um pH they're intra
they're segmented they terminate intra
intasc thank you and uh and also they're
often innovated by different nerve
branches not only do they terminate
intasc but they are innovated
differently so they'll have different
nerve branches going to different
muscles and uh just to tease people
it'll give them a little tease uh we're
currently uh through my lab Brett and I
are currently working on a paper looking
at hamstrings different hamstring
exercises and preliminary results
clearly show that the different by
training them at different joints
training the hamstrings at different
joints you're able to Target different
portions of the hamstrings now do you
have statist statistical power on that
yet Mr
do I I like how this works you tell me
to keep my mouth shut about it but then
you get to get all the
glory we are keeping our mouth shut
we're just spreading their appetites a
little so so let's talk about specifics
so
uh essentially what I was getting at
earlier before I was rudely interrupted
uh was that uh with some muscles it's
Common Sense the deltoids and the pecs
for example you know that if you want to
work the front the side or the rear
delts that that's just common sense you
can feel it you can see it with the pecs
we've always kind of seen if you want to
work up upper pecs do more incline and
and you know incline press dumbbell
incline um incline flies low pulley
crossovers but uh but some of the
muscles it's not as um it's not as
common
sense um I will tell you I've come
across articles for almost every muscle
at this point in time every muscle and
even like parts of a like cuz that's
like with the deltoids you've got some
clear differentiation there you know you
look at the muscle on an anatomy chart
and it looks you can see like okay that
head is going to function completely
differently from that head but with some
muscles it's not as
clearcut and Recent research so we've
got it we've got Recent research that
that has not just showed that you get
different well so Brad let's talk about
first of all how can you show different
levels of activation what what
technology can you use to show different
levels of the different muscle Muses get
worked differently during ex exercise
I'm talking about acute studies here
yeah and the two ways the two most
common ways are through EMG analysis
that's what we're using in our study and
also MRI T2 MRI where they look at
changes uh within the muscle under MRI
immediately after training well if you
do immediately afterwards then that's
going to show you which which um it
shows fluid shifts the weighted T2 shows
fluid shifts so if you do it immediately
after the exercise then you it shows
more metabolic stress which is
interesting because that goes back to
Brad's article so you can show which got
activated more and which had more you
know metabolic demands but if you wait a
couple days now you're not looking at
more activation and metabolic stress
you're looking at more muscle
damage um and so there's going to be
more fluid accumulated in the muscle
that's damaged more so that's kind of a
aspect of
MRI whereas with EMG it it's it's a
useful component of showing activation
now uh Brad did you I couldn't I wasn't
paying attention did you talk about what
we're doing right now did you hint elude
to what we're looking at I just wet
everyone's appetite we don't want to get
into
specifics the study is still underway
and uh we should have some data
hopefully uh official data I would say
within a month and uh hopefully we'll
have publication shortly and then we can
tell the world okay so uh basically
there there's a prior study using MRI
using weighted T2 looking at uh looking
at muscle damage in the
hamstrings um this was I was actually
involved in this paper this was
published the migi mendiguchia was the
main author he's my friend from Spain
and he showed that uh or we showed that
if you have a if you do a walking lunge
or sorry Ecentric lunge versus an
Ecentric lying leg curl you get more
damage with the lunge you get more
damage in the upper hamstring area
whereas with the Ecentric leg curl you
get more damage in the lower hamstring
area uh there actually were a group of
authors who responded who wrote a letter
to the editor they made some very good
points but we um offered a rebuttal and
made some very good points as
well um I have come across articles in
the last year with the lumbar extensors
with the rectus femoris uh we saw an
article in the jscr on Cales turning
your feet out versus in activates the
calves
differently quads we'll talk about this
research in a little bit quads we've got
some really fascinating research that's
emerged uh so we talked about hamstrings
oh glutes glutes there is actually a
studies from like the
1940s um and 60s showing differential
activation with the upper and lower um
segments of the glutes uh for example if
you just lift your leg straight out to
the side frontal plane hip abduction you
activate the upper gutus Maximus but the
lower stays
silent
um uh I'm just going up the um going up
the chain with abdominals there is uh
research showing some really good
research lately showing that the uh the
the rectus abdominis muscle activation
changes depending on whether the
movement is more oriented towards the
spine and kind of like the rib cage like
a crunch movement versus working more on
the pelvis like a posterior pelvic tilt
as in a reverse crunch movement the re
the the postor pelvic tilt will will
activate more lower
abdominals um he we already talked about
deltoids we already talked about I do
want to add as far as the uh the lower
abdominals go one of the issues that we
have when people say well it doesn't
that it really there isn't any
activation some of the studies have just
used the straight leg raise without a
posterior pelvic tilt and that really is
a big issue that uh if you just raise
your legs you're not there's no reason
that the lower abdominal region would be
activated contrary to what people think
the activation it seems is through you
have to be able to engage a posterior
pelvic til to achieve that and that is a
limitation there's been several studies
I know student McGill did one where it
was just a straight leg raise didn't
show anything and you wouldn't
anticipate it would it's basically just
hip flexion it is not uh you're not
engaging the lower abdominals actively M
they they their group did
a study probably a year and a half ago
that did show
differentiation whether the abdomino
were acting on the pelvis or not so
they've and and and heck Even Stu Mill
did a a study with belly dancers showing
that the belly dancers could completely
they were this was insane they could
completely
isolate parts of certain muscles like
the rectus abdominis they they could
completely activate one portion over
another that's how they can do those
crazy Maneuvers but with ex with most
abdominal exercises you get some
activation but when you are it depends
on what joint you're acting on um that's
with the rectus abdominis but my my
point is to show that you get um you can
see selective activation I think a study
came out with lats if I'm not mistaken
Rec more recently or maybe it was just
oh you know what maybe it was looking at
the fibers maybe it was an anatomic so
sometimes you see modeling studies
here's the real to me the real exciting
aspect of this so we can talk about well
so what people can say so what there's
been the recent Studies have shown the
wakahara studies hold on before we get
into the training studies Brad I want
you to describe the the quadriceps
research so we've we've talked about
activation but here's something really
exciting the Brad reviewed he was one of
the reviewers for an article and this
one looked at uh the quadriceps and
there have been studies that show with
for example with leg extensions you get
more hypertrophy in the proximal
quadriceps compared sorry in the distal
quadriceps compared to the proximal
quadriceps the lower quads will get more
muscular than the upper quads from leg
extensions but Brad this did not have to
do with activation did it what did it
have to do with yes well that's where I
was going with this that there's
somewhat conflicting evidence that this
had to do with the lack of oxygenation
the hypoxia within the muscle they
attributed uh to Greater um results and
it's been shown there's a hypoxic effect
can increase the metabolic demands
increase metabolic stress and of other
potential we're not even sure what all
the mechanisms are that might be
mediating the hypertrophic response but
that the same uh M that was through
mamoto that he is part of the group with
wakahara now wakahara and this is to me
real quick real ex I'm gonna cut you off
again sorry so further explain that when
you're doing a leg extension you're
getting more blood flow to the upper
quadriceps or or just less you're
getting less blood flow right they're
saying there's more compression of the
uh the circulatory system in the lower
region so it's cutting off the
oxygenation levels they use Ox Techni
When Brad says hypoxia you're getting
less oxygen to the lower quadriceps when
you do leg
extensions and because of that you're
getting more metabolic stress in that in
those areas and greater hypertrophy and
if you look at bodybuilders compared to
powerlifters bodybuilders do leg
extensions you know they're they're they
do a lot more isolation work they do
have larger quadriceps when you look at
bodybuilders compared to powerlifters
you'll see more hamstring development um
because they're doing the leg curls
they're um you know they're working more
there is it just plays a case for
variety in movement which we'll touch on
later but Brad's been trying mentioned
this a couple times and I want to
properly introduce this so we've got all
these mechanistic studies fine we're
showing greater activation in the
muscles but that just like you know
acute studies just let us form good
theories but really you want to see a
good training study a longitudinal study
showing okay I did this exercise this
exercise activates this certain portion
more I did it for a period of time and I
showed greater results I showed actual
growth like more growth not just
activation you actually showed more
hypertrophy in this area so Brad are
there any studies linking increased
activation to increased
hypertrophy yeah there's two Studies by
wakahara and mamoto the one who did the
study on the quads actually is part of
that group so they are they're doing
similar research obviously and the
wakara studies actually did two was they
looked at the triceps triceps break ey
and they found that the activation
of the muscle through MRI they used MRI
activation was correlated with
hypertrophy so they did an acute study
looking at where the uh muscle was being
activated then they did a uh training
study it was I believe a 12-week study
uh doing one one of the studies used a
line tricep extension and the other one
used a close grip bench press and both
of them they actually found there was
different activations with those
exercises and where the activation
happened correlated with the uh
hypertrophy that was seen so really
interesting and it really goes to show
or so this was a this was a huge win for
bodybuilders who've been saying this all
along you need to do multiple movements
for a body part because where where you
activate a muscle the most is where it
grows the most it doesn't just grow
uniformly across the entire muscle so
theoretically if you do a ver you know
several exercises you can end up working
the entire muscle to its greatest degree
yeah and if I can so to me I think not
only is that important but we need then
need so we can extrapolate this and I
think we want to T tie this into the
variety aspect that uh there are some
people some Fitness professionals that
say I just do your basic big moves do
you do squats do bench press uh do
shoulder press uh do deadlifts and like
a row and then and that's all you ever
need to do like that's the big five like
squats deadlifts bench press military
press and Ben overose
or maximum hypertrophy that is that is a
misguided statement so certainly that's
going to get you stronger but even
something like now you mentioned before
and this is why I do think it's
important to mention we talk about like
the deltoids and people say well a
shoulder press just do a shoulder press
and you get all three heads of the
deltoid so why bother doing your
isolation type moves your targeted
movements not the case if you look at a
shoulder press the muscle that is
directly opposing gravity is going to
take the brunt of the uh of the
activation so what is directly opposing
gravity during a shoulder press your
anterior Del and this is actually been
shown recently there's been a a recent
study that actually looked at that uh so
you're going to get a lot more it's yeah
are you gon to get some middle out yes
you're G to get some posterior a little
but certainly not to the degree and if
you just do shoulder presses you're
going to have significantly
overdeveloped anterior adults VV the
middle and the posterior adults I think
um with my EMG research and I think I've
seen several studies but yeah you get
the most as as as um normalized MVC you
get the highest activation in the front
followed by the middle and then the rear
delts they get activated well and they
even the rear delts will activate just
to stabilize the shoulder to kind of
that's correct um but they're not if you
really want to maximize your activation
on the rear delt you have to do rear
delt raises or yeah you got to work it
all three
basically Brad which grip is best for
the rear delt
Rays well we did find that a neutral
grip was better than a pronated grip uh
for um for activating now how much of it
if you're a bodybuilder probably enough
to make a difference and I would
recommend it if you're just a
recreational train trainee I'd probably
say just use whatever is more
comfortable for you that was a paper we
got published that was just published a
couple months ago in the jscr correct um
so okay so uh we've been talking about
variety we've talked about the miar
study the wakahara
studies um we talk some things that we
we've got to talk about got to talk
about more about variety here so uh what
what what more can we talk about we've
got about 10 minutes left Brad so some
things with VAR how do you incorporate
variety and training so first Brad talk
about uh active insufficiency and why
this is important to know for
hypertrophy
yeah so we know that just changing the
planes as we talked about let's say for
shoulders and and various other
movements for the the lats doing rows in
the sagittal plane rows in the
horizontal plane transverse plane row
and thatat pull Downs or chins in the
frontal PL so it's certainly changing
your planes a good way but the concept
of active insufficiency is really
important to understand and that says
that a muscle when a two-joint muscle so
a muscle that crosses two joints and
there are many of them in the body uh if
you stretch that muscle and place one
end under a stretch and then and then um
be active at the other end you will
increase its Force production and if you
shorten the muscle at one end and then
act upon it at the other that will
decrease its Force production so it
gives us a lot a huge amount of variety
that we can accomplish and thus gives us
a huge amount of potential for sculpting
our body for uh targeting different
muscles so let's take you uh you can
that plays a um that's important to know
not only for work for that muscle that
two joint muscle but for also working
the synergist that it works with so give
us an example of the calves and the
Solus okay yeah so the classic one is
the uh the gastr and the Solus so the
gastro crosses We Know Two Joints where
the Solus Solus only crosses the ankle
joint whereas the gastrock not only is
it a plantar flexor a ex center of the
uh ankle but it also is a a knee flexer
it assists the hamstrings in flexing the
knee so if you fle people whenever they
do Nordic hamstring curls or glute ham
raises beginners will always cramp up in
the calves and they don't understand why
and it's because the calves work as knee
flexors right so if you are doing a
seated uh calf raise the H the gas stro
already is shortened because it is the
knee is flexed so obviously with the
joint is flexion if you Flex the knee
you will shorten it so if you shorten
the gastr the Solus is therefore going
to have to take over a majority of the
work and that's actually been shown
recently too in a study whereas if you
do a standing hamstring uh a standing uh
calf raise the gasr will be lengthened
at the knee joint and thus it will act
to a much greater degree in the plantar
in plantar flection so let's talk about
other two joint muscles you've got
hamstrings you've got rectus femoris
you've got biceps and triceps so with
the let's talk about the rectus Fus when
you are and the hamstrings the rectus
foror in the hamstrings in a squat for
example don't in a lunge they don't
change length much they they might
lengthen depending on pelvic tilt like
if you're in anterior tilt if you go
down into anterior tilt they might
lengthen a little bit but it's not going
to be that much so they they're they're
not going to activate that high because
they're not being stretched uh much and
so um so if so if you're doing a squat
or even a leg a leg extension where
you're bent over the rectus florus is
not at a good length um and so the vases
are going to work harder if you think of
a barbell hip thrust the hamstrings are
shortened and as you thrust the weight
up the hamstrings get shorter and
shorter As you move into hip
uh hip hyp hip extension and hip
hyperextension hamstrings keep getting
shorter the glutes have to keep doing
more and more and more so if you want to
you know if you're doing hip extension
and you want the glutes to do more do
bent legged hip extension work if you
want the hamstrings to do more
straighten that leg out if you want uh
the rectus Fus to do more you want to be
you don't want to be bent over in hip
flexion you want to be more upright and
do I mean theoretically you'd want to do
like leg extensions from a lying
position or something if you really
wanted to focus and maybe combine some
sort of hip flexion moment with it or
something but anyway I've never I guess
I haven't seen a study how to
maximize the I was gonna say also that's
the what you just spoke about is reason
why certainly with the hamstrings you
need to do direct hamstring work you
can't just rely on squats leg presses
lunges to to develop your hamstrings
because they're not going to be as
nearly as active as your glutes and your
quads certainly your vasti in those
exercises you need to do the single
joint movements your remain and
deadlifts your uh hamstring your leg
curls um and we can also talk the upper
body you mentioned like the triceps well
if you we know that the long head of the
triceps crosses the shoulder joint
whereas the medial and lateral heads
don't so if you want to Target the long
head you bring your arm up into flexion
your shoulder into flexion and that
stretches the long head and do let's say
an overhead tricep extension where if
you're doing a press down Kickback one
of those type of exercises the L head
will be shorten now because you're
bringing it into extension the shoulder
joint and thus the medial and lateral
heads will take over and if you wanted
to work the long head of the biceps more
in a curl what Would You Do Well
generally the L head of the biceps uh
because because of its attachment uh
that's a little harder to functionally
differentiate but bringing the um
bringing it back the it's like a drag
curl or a incline curl will work the
long head more um as well as you you'll
also you'll get the short head more if
you uh because the long head also is a
uh abductor so if you're doing this you
can Target the short head to a greater
degree um okay so we have about five
minutes left we've talked about active
insufficiency we've talked about
functional differentiation now let's
just talk about variety How can I um how
can I incorporate variety into training
without being like you know muscle like
without being like P90X muscle
confusion you don't want to just have
too much variety there's a sweet spot so
I always like a um an article that
Charles Staley and Keith snidman wrote
several years ago for tation and they
called it same but
different you want to stick to this you
know the best movements but you vary the
slightly so that you know you're doing
them differently over time so and this
is what Westside barbell Club does with
their powerlifting they will do you know
they pick a Max effort lift squats
deadlifts or good mornings but they have
a million different ways to do it you
can vary what are the things you can
vary Brad you can vary now just talking
about exercise positioning you can
stance stance width foot flare range of
motion um barbell loading where it's
load
you know for squats you could do wide
stance squats narrow stance squats you
could turn the feet out more you could
do more box squats where you sit back
more and keep vertical tibia you could
do more full like Olympic squats where
you sit straight down and let the knees
travel forward more you get more dors
flexion you could do front squats back
squats High bar low Bar zercher Box you
you could do so many different types of
squats there's so many different types
of deadlifts so many T ways to you know
there's different ways to bench press
with a wider grip with a closer grip um
with a pause on your chest there's so
many ways to incorporate variety but
what so that's just with exercise
technique and and loading but what else
with program design how can you
incorporate variety well I think the
other thing now if your goal is
hypertrophy um incorporating single
joint movements is a very important
aspect uh to compliment focus of the
program no that the focus would be on
your multi-joint movements but that you
do incorporate single joint movements
into the routine that the if you're
focusing on strength you can very much
limit in my tumble opinion very much
limit the single joint movements that
you do uh to a large extent unless
you're just looking for the specific
weaknesses you might have but for
hypertrophy if you really want to
optimize hypertrophy and now again we're
talking so for the if you're just a
recreational bodybuilder or whatever and
you're not it's not uh your goal to to
step on stage how much that's going to
matter probably not a lot but that is
the difference in someone who really
wants to take their physique to that
next level uh that's where you really
have to start focusing on that so this
is where I think it gets a little
convoluted and people often talk about
well you just need to do this you just
stick to the basics whatever the more
you want to optimize a a goal such as
hypertrophy the more you're going to
have to start to uh to focus on these
others the smaller things to get that
optimization that's where you kind of
eek out that last 5% uh of your gains so
you always want the goal the the focus
to be on get get stronger at the
compound lifts but never get if
hypertrophy is a goal never get so get
stronger at the expense of good form and
using the right muscles to do the
job and then
incorporate uh variety by using
isolation movements and things like that
and just add those on and you don't
always have to be thinking Progressive
overload with these isolation movements
sometimes focus on quality sometimes go
for the pump sometimes do higher reps
sometimes lower reps sometimes slower
Tempo sometimes faster Tempo sometimes
less rest period sometimes more um
sometimes you know do different do hit
you know sometimes use band resistance
sometimes cable sometimes dumbbell
there's so many ways to incorporate
variety so Brad we have have it is 5:15
we have taken up our 30
minutes that is it for this uh week's uh
BNB connection I hope you enjoyed the
show uh don't be afraid to give us some
ideas for the next show because we're
all ears if you've got ideas for us and
hopefully and just to add also please uh
uh add some comments in the discussion
if you feel uh differently we'd like to
hear about it uh to us really what we're
looking to do is to
uh provoke thought to stir discussion
and debate and to hopefully Advance the
uh the field in this manner so that we
can really take a more scientific
approach to what sometimes is H is
bogged down in Bro
Science thank you very much for watching